July the 6th, 2001. I I remember it like
it was yesterday. I told you I was in
this position where I was training
Middle Eastern intelligence services in
counterterrorism operations. [music]
And so we had this delegation of, you
know, four mid-level guys, majors and
lieutenant colonels. And uh totally
normal liaison visit. They come in the
morning. We have a day of briefings. We
take them upstairs to meet the director.
They shake his hand. They get a little
photo op. We exchange gifts. I drop them
off at the hotel and I tell them rest
up. I'll be back in 3 hours. And you
take them to Ruth's Chris steakhouse.
And then the next day you do it with a
different intelligence service and a
different one again the next day after
that. [music]
So that day uh July the 6th, 2001, I had
booked a [music] 30 minute briefing with
this junior like 25year-old kid on
[music] al-Qaeda. So the time came for
the briefing and instead of this young
kid in comes Kofheer Black, the director
of counterterrorism and a woman who was
not affectionately known as the
red-headed devil who was portrayed in uh
Zero Dark 30. So they come in together
and I was so surprised I stood up and I
said, "Oh," I said, "Gentlemen, this is
Kofheblack. He's the director of the
counterterrorism center here at the CIA.
And this is the chief of operations for
the Osama bin Laden unit. I was shocked,
like speechless. And they sat down and
Kofheer looks at these guys and just
goes right into it. He says, "Something
terrible is going to happen. We don't
know where or when, but we know it'll be
an attack on an unprecedented scale." He
said, "We're picking up chatter from the
al-Qaeda training camps where the
instructors are on the phone with their
students and they're crying and saying,
"I'll see you in paradise." We're
hearing code words for a massive attack.
The honey salesman is coming with vast
quantities of honey or there's going to
be an enormous wedding or a great
football match is coming. They're all
codes for an attack, but we don't know
where or when it's going to be. He said,
"I'm begging you. If you have any
sources inside al-Qaeda, please help
us." And they just sat there looking at
him. And I was like, "Seriously?" So, he
got up, shook their hands, we finished
the day. I uh sent them back to the
hotel. And then I went to Kofheer's
office to thank him. I said, "Keoffer,
wanted to thank you for spending the
time with these guys, but I got to ask
you, I don't work on al-Qaeda. Were you
saying that for their benefit or were
you serious?" and he said, "Oh, I'm
deadly serious. Something terrible is
going to happen." And then September
11th, it's kind of a quaint story now,
but on on the morning of September 11th,
Kofer and I had a meeting scheduled with
Condi Rice. She was the National
Security Adviser at the time, and it was
over the stupidest reason. The
Government Printing Office, this obscure
little government agency that prints all
the official reports, was going to print
a report that literally nobody would
ever read called Foreign Policy of the
United States, Greece, Turkey, Cyprus,
1949 to 1967. Nobody's ever going to
read that. But there is a law in the
United States that says that if an
official of the United States outs the
identity of a recruited asset, we h we
have to offer that asset protection,
which means American citizenship, a
house, money to get started. Well, there
were still three guys like in their 90s
that would have been outed with
publication of these declassified
documents. It just never occurred to
anybody that someone would still be
alive whom the American embassy was
meeting in the 40s, right? So, we had
this meeting with Condi to ask her just
to pull those cables out of the out of
the book, right? We're not asking her to
make up different names. We're just pull
cables out. Nobody's going to know.
They're nobody's going to know the
difference. So, the driver called me and
said he was ready to pick us up and he's
outside the west uh entrance. So, I
walked over to Kofheer's office to say,
"The driver's here." And his secretary
had a little TV on her on her desk. Back
in those days, you couldn't watch TV on
your computer, right? So, she had this
little tiny TV.
>> One of the one of the towers of the
World Trade Center was on fire. I said,
"What happened to the World Trade
Center?" And she said, "A plane flew
into it." And I always say, because I'm
a genius, I said, "You know what? That
happened once before in 1931.
A plane flew into the Empire State
Building, but it was really foggy and
pouring down rain. I said, "It's so
crystal clear today. How can you not see
that you're flying into the World Trade
Center?" And as soon as the words came
out of my mouth, the second plane hit.
And she turned to me and she said, "Did
you see that or did I imagine it?" And I
ran back to my office and I said, "Guys,
two planes just flew into both towers of
the World Trade Center. I think we're
under attack. I think this is what
Kofheer was talking about." So we all
run into what what was then called the
bullpen. The the main office back then
of the counterterrorism center was this
enormous room where there were private
offices all around the perimeter of the
room and then everybody else sat in
cubicles. Well, there were so many
cubicles that we had to name the
pathways. So it was like Bin Laden
Boulevard, Hezbollah Highway, right? We
named one after George Tannet and one
after a previous head of
counterterrorism. So you could say if
you're meeting somebody, I'm at the
intersection of Winston Wy Way and
Hezbollah Highway and they would know
where to find you. So we all run up
there. There were these TVs that were
mounted on from the ceiling and each TV
was on different networks. It was like
CNN, Fox, MSNBC, BBC, uh, Canal PL, the
Russians, you know, everybody had a TV,
dead silence in the office. We're
watching the World Trade Center burn.
And then somebody behind me shouts,
"Will someone please lead?" And it was
like slapping Kofer in the face. He's
like, "Right, you go to the director's
office and tell him X. You go to
security and tell him something else.
you go to operations and you know
whatever and we all continue to just
stand there and watch it and then the
Pentagon gets hit and then somebody says
we should probably assume that the next
plane is meant for us. We didn't know
the White House, the capital, us logical
targets. Nobody budged. So one of the
cops came in we the CIA has its own
police force called the special
protective officers. And so he came in
he says everybody evacuate. Nobody
moved. He came back in 45 minutes later
and said, "If you don't evacuate, you'll
be placed under arrest." So, everybody
evacuated. But imagine, you know,
whatever 10, 15, 20,000 people all
leaving the parking lot at exactly the
same time. It took me 2 hours to get out
of my parking space. Might as well have
just stayed in the building.
>> I could have walked home. I only lived
at seven miles from the from the
headquarters. So, finally, I got into
the George Washington Parkway. I got
about halfway to my apartment and it was
gridlock. So, I just abandoned my car on
the side of the highway. I walked the
last three and a half miles. I I could
see the Pentagon burning from my car.
And I remember saying out loud, "How
could this happen? How could we allow
this to happen?" And my then girlfriend
called me. She was on the sixth floor of
headquarters. She later became my wife.
And uh she said, "Where are you?" I
said, "I I just abandoned my car on the
GW Parkway. Where are you?" She said,
"I'm just getting out of headquarters."
I said, "You're not going to be able to
make it past the halfway point. Just
meet me at my house or my apartment."
So, she finally met me at my apartment.
We we went to the roof and just watched
the Pentagon burn for a couple of hours.
And then I said, "We should try to give
blood or something." Well, there there
were lines to give blood that that were
blocks long. And then finally, I said,
"This is ridiculous. We we should get
back to work." So, we walked back to my
car. I drove over the the grassy median,
went back to headquarters, and then I
didn't leave for the next four days. We
I I just baldled up my jacket and slept
under the desk, and we took a bolt
cutters and and cut the chains on the
cafeteria. We had to write the Marriott
again cuz they had the food uh
concession. We had to write the Marriott
a check for $10,000 cuz we stole all
their food and we cooked it and we put
it on folding tables in the hallway so
people could just graze as they were
working. But everybody worked. And then
like everybody else in the building, the
very next day, I went into the deputy
director's office. I said, "You've got
to send me to Afghanistan. I'm one of
the only fluent Arabic speakers in the
office. You have to send me." Uh, relax.
Okay, relax, relax. Take it easy. We're
not really sure what's going on yet. All
right. I went three times over the next
six weeks. You've got to send me to
Afghanistan. Finally, I ran into a guy
that I knew, an old-timer. He was in his
70s then, Billy Wah. legendary
special forces guy. 17 Purple Hearts,
one short of the national record. Even
his license plate, it said 17 hits and
it was a a Purple Heart license plate.
Very cool, legendary guy. So, I ran into
him. We had just done an operation
together in the Middle East and we got
back like two or three days before 911.
So, I ran into him and I said, "Billy,
where you been?" And he goes, "Been in
Afghanistan." I go, "You have? What are
you doing there? He looks at me, he
goes, I've been killing people. What do
you think I've been doing? I said,
that's why they haven't sent me because
I was always the good cop and they
didn't need translators.
>> They're not interrogating anybody.
They're just blowing their brains out.
So, I was like, "Okay, okay." So, I I
said, "I'm going to try one more time."
I went back into the deputy director's
office and I said, 'You have to send me
to Afghanistan. And if you don't, I'm
going to quit and I'm going to go
straight to Exxon with my Arabic and
make triple what I make here and I'm not
looking back. He's like, all right, take
it easy. Can you go to Pakistan? I said,
yes. When? Tomorrow. Yes. What do you
want me to do? He said, I want you to be
chief of counterterrorism operations. I
said, good. So, I I called my
girlfriend. I said, I got to go to
Pakistan tomorrow. She said, 'Okay, how
long? I said, 'I don't know, 6 months, 9
months, a year, I don't know. She says,
'Okay, I'll meet you at your place. I'll
help you pack. And then she drove me to
the airport the next morning and I went
to Pakistan. So enhanced interrogation
techniques, as they were approved by the
Justice Department, were mostly not
something that I would call torture.
Like if I grab you by the shirt and I
say, "Damn you, answer my questions."
That's not torture. If uh the the next
the next most serious one was called the
belly slap, right? It makes a cracking
sound. Makes a handprint. A little bit
humiliating. That's not torture.
>> But are you like naked, chained up?
>> Not yet. That comes
>> keyword yet.
>> Yeah. A smack across the face. That's
not very nice. But it's probably not
torture. But then you get into things
like strip the guy naked, chain him to
an eyebolt in the ceiling, and make it
so he can't kneel or sit or lay or get
comfortable in any way. chill the cell
to 50 degrees Fahrenheit and then throw
a bucket of ice water on them every
hour. We murdered uh prisoners with that
technique. It's called the cold cell.
Sleep deprivation is another one. Uh Don
Rumsfeld was the secretary of defense at
the time. He famously said that he
didn't believe that there was such a
thing called sleep deprivation because
he said, "Look at me. I have a standup
desk in my office. I don't even have a a
chair and I'll stand there and work for
24 hours, sometimes longer than 24
hours. That's not what we were talking
about. What we're talking about is being
stripped naked and chained to that
eyebolt so you can't get comfortable
knowing that the American Psychological
Association has done studies showing
that people begin to lose their minds at
day seven with no sleep. They begin to
die from organ failure at day nine, but
the CIA was was authorized to keep
patients patients to keep prisoners
awake for up to 12 days. Well, we
murdered prisoners doing that. The
Justice Department never said we could
murder people. They said we could use
these techniques, which are not torture.
They're enhanced parts of the
interrogation. Well, that was just
silly. Let me give you some background
first. MK Ultra was a program that
started in the early 1950s and it
started by accident. We had a source who
turned out to be a fabricator saying the
Russians are doing mind control
experiments. We were like, "Oh my god,
we're going to be behind the Russians.
All right, we got to do our own mind
control experiments. The Russians are
doing ESP experiments." We said, "Oh my
god, we have to hire all the the
psychics in America and try and get them
to do mind control." So we came up with
this thing that was called MK Ultra and
it was composed of several different sub
operations MK chipwit for example. So we
were doing things like what would happen
if we gave people LSD and they didn't
know it. Let's try that. See what
happens. Well who should we do it to?
Let's do it to our own people. Just see
what happens. Well I'll tell you what
happens. They start jumping out of
windows and off of roofs of buildings
and committing suicide. They're like,
"That didn't work." Okay, why don't we
hire prostitutes?
This is true. We'll hire prostitutes in
San Francisco. We'll have them pick up
John's. We'll bring the John's back to a
safe house that we control. We'll dose
them with LSD. We'll tie them up and
interrogate them and see if they'll tell
us their deepest secrets. No, they just
went nuts. That's all that happened. And
then we release them. And then they're
just wandering the streets of San
Francisco nuts. Then they said, "How
about if we come up with a germ and we
spread the germ all around San Francisco
and see if people get sick." So they
came up with this germ. They waited
until a really foggy day when the air is
very heavy and it sits on the ground,
right? Cuz what's fog? It's a cloud that
sits on the ground. And within days, 11
people went to hospital emergency rooms
with this rare strain of upper
respiratory infection. We're like, "Hey,
now we can do that in Havana, in Moscow,
in East Berlin." But none of this led
to, you know, reading minds or Manurion
candidates or none of it worked. But it
was brutal. And we made people insane.
We made people commit suicide. We split
families. And this was monstrous. Well,
it it became public in 1975 in in the
Church and Pike Committee hearings on
Capitol Hill. So, it lasted from 1952 to
1975. And chairman uh Church, senior
senator from Idaho, specifically ordered
the CIA director not to destroy the
documents related to MK Ultra. He
immediately went back to headquarters
and destroyed 80% of the documents. So,
we only have a little historical
understanding of what happened with MK
Ultra. Everything else was was shredded.
People ask me all the time, is there MK
Ultra today? Honestly, I have no idea.
It's not called MK Ultra, but it's
impossible to know what the CIA is doing
on these mind control issues. Now,
they're doing other things
technologically that we know thanks to
Wikileaks and Josh Schulty and the uh
Vault 7 revelations, we know that they
can take remote control of your car and
make you drive off a bridge.
>> Any car,
>> any car, any car that has a computer in
it, which is every car, unless you're
driving a, you know, 57 Chevy or
something. uh we know that they can take
any smart TV any smart TV and turn the
speaker into a microphone so that it
broadcasts what's being said in the room
even while the TV is off. Another thing
that they did was they infected
computers domestically which is illegal
but then in the code they embedded lines
of code written in either Farsy or
Cerrillic.
>> That's marble right project marble.
>> Correct. So they could point say, "Oh,
it wasn't us. It was the Russians, the
Iranians. They did it. Look the code.
They forgot to translate these lines of
code. They're still in Russian and
Farsy." No, it was it was us. So we
don't really know what they are doing.
And I and I'll I'll say this. I'm going
to caveat this by saying I've been out
of the CIA for 21 years now. That is a
lifetime technologically speaking. It's
a different world today than it was when
I left the CIA. God knows what they can
do that we haven't found out yet. Abu
Zabeta is in Afghanistan. Abu Zaba is in
Syria. It's like, oh my god, this is a
terrorist superman. But it was two of
them. We [music] didn't know cuz he's
out out doing all this different stuff.
Turned out he wasn't. Actually, the CIA
will never permit him to be charged in a
court of law. The torture report tells
[music] us that the CIA has made a
policy decision that Abu Zubeda will
never leave Guantanamo ever. And when he
does die, eventually he'll be cremated
and his ashes thrown into the Caribbean.
Billy was in Sudan working for Kofheer
Black. Kofheer Black was the CI.
>> No, he was US.
>> Oh, CIA.
>> CIA, but he was the senior. The term of
art we're supposed to use is the senior
CIA officer in country. The CIA does not
acknowledge any such thing as a station.
So whenever we talk about working
overseas, that person was the senior CIA
officer in country.
>> Okay.
>> Okay. So Billy's off one day and he
decides to go down to the uh vegetable
market and buy some vegetables for the
week. He goes down with a buddy of his,
also from the embassy. And you know,
they're the only two white guys in in
cartoon, they think. So they're in the
vegetable market and Billy looks and
he's looking at this guy and he says to
his friend, "That's Carlos the Jackal."
And the guy's like, "What? No, it's
not." And Billy said, "Yeah, that's
Carlos the Jackal." "No, I don't think
so, Billy." Billy said, "I'm sure it
is." They go back to the embassy.
Kofheer's in his office on a what do you
call this? Elliptical machine. Yeah.
>> He's an elliptical machine. And uh Billy
walks in. He says, "Keoffer, I just saw
Carlos the Jackal." Kofheer says, "Get
the [__] out of here."
>> He said, "No, I'm telling you, I was in
the vegetable market and I saw him and
I'm sure it's him." And he's like,
"Well, I think you're nuts, but if it's
Carlos the Jackal, we're going to have
to confirm it."
>> How old was Billy at this time?
>> Oh, he was in his 70s.
>> Okay. Yeah.
>> Maniac.
>> Late 60s, maybe.
>> Wow.
>> Yeah. Incredibly great shape after
having been shot more than a dozen times
over the course of three wars. So, uh,
he went back down to that vegetable
market every single day for a month. And
then they saw Carlos again. So what they
decided to do was they hired a couple of
Sudin guys to stage a fist fight. Um in
in Muslim countries it's very very
unusual for you to ever witness um
physical violence between people. People
don't like you know we have videos on
YouTube of Karen's they load load a
thousand new ones every day
>> in the Middle East. No, people don't do
things like that. So they hired these
two Sudin guys that were just down there
in the market. um you know, you give
them 10 bucks a piece and just tell them
duke it out. So they duke it out and of
course everybody forms a circle around
them because this is so unusual. And
Carlos comes to the circle to watch the
fight and he's like craning his neck to
try to get a better view and Billy's got
a camera. Click click click click click
click click click. So he goes back to
the embassy. They send the pictures to
CIA headquarters and they say, "Oh my
god, it's Carlos the Jackal." Well,
Billy had followed him back to his house
so they knew where he lived. And what
they ended up doing, I'm not sure how
much detail I should get in. They ended
up Carlos had a Carlos had a dental
problem. And so, um, what you do is you
get the dentist to say, "Hey, time for a
checkup. Why don't you come on in?" And
then you give him gas. And then when he
wakes up, he's on a plane on his way to
France.
>> Oh my god.
>> Wow.
Yeah, that was Billy. Hero with capital
letters. Hero. Didn't even have to touch
the guy. No. Just got to his dentist.
>> Yeah, that's it. That's incredible.
>> Sometimes the best operations are the
simplest.
>> When you captured Abu Zabeta and he got
shot, how how many years has it been
since you captured him?
>> Uh almost 22.
>> 22. And he was Do you remember how old
he was?
>> Yeah. To the best of my recollection, he
was like 25 or 27, something like that.
He was very young. I remember being
struck by his youth. I was young at the
time. I was 30. Let me think. What was
I? I was 37.
>> Oh, wow.
>> Mhm. And I remember thinking, "Wow, this
is al-Qaeda. This is what we're so
afraid of." You know, he's just a young
guy, one of the most wanted men in the
world.
>> And that was probably one of the one of
the most defining moments of your career
in the CIA.
>> Oh, it was it was the defining event of
my of my life.
>> What would you say to him if you got to
meet him again? And do you think there's
a possibility? Would you ever want to go
like have a meeting with him in
Guantanamo and talk to him?
>> I'd like to. I've spoken to his attorney
uh many times. You know, this is the
reason why I'm still talking about this
22 years later. We believed at the time
that Abu Zuba was the number three in
al-Qaeda. He was identified by to us by
the White House as the number three in
al-Qaeda. Um he was identified in Time
magazine which was a major publication
at the time as the number three in
al-Qaeda. uh we knew that he had founded
al-Qaeda's safe house in Peshawar,
Pakistan called the House of Martyrs and
that's where people would stay as they
were preparing to go to Afghanistan uh
for for training, terrorist training.
Not only did he establish the House of
Martyrs, he also established al-Qaeda's
two training camps in southern
Afghanistan in Helman province and in
Kandahar. Um so we knew this was a bad
guy. If you were already in the fight
and you wanted to go home, Abu Zubeda
would forge a passport and get you
tickets home. If you wanted to join the
fight, he would get you to the House of
Martyrs and then into Afghanistan and
then from Afghanistan, he would get you
to wherever it was you were supposed to
go. So, this was a bad guy, but he was
not the number three in al-Qaeda.
>> No,
>> no, he had never joined al-Qaeda. He
talked about it, but he had never sworn
an oath to uh Osama bin Laden. So he was
viewed by Bin Laden and by the al-Qaeda
leadership as an independent sort of a
friendly independent
>> like a guy like well like that bin Laden
wouldn't give him a wink and a nod of
approval like
>> right okay
>> now the bigger problem for us at the CIA
and we didn't know this until 2005
was that Abu Zubeda had a first cousin
who was also named Abu Zubeta and so
that Abu Zubeda was in Montana and then
when 9/11 hit he said oh [__] I got to
get out of here. And he ran to Jordan.
So our sister agencies are picking up
intelligence here, there, and
everywhere. Out of the air, out of the
sky. Abu Zuba is in Aman. He's doing
this. Abu Zabeda's in Pakistan. He's
doing that. Abu Zubed is in Afghanistan.
Abu Zaba's in Syria. It's like, oh my
god, this is a terrorist superman,
right? But it was two of them.
>> Two of them.
>> Two of them. We didn't know.
And so we thought, well, if if he's able
to move from country to country and he's
plotting all these different operations,
we got to stop this guy. We know that
bin Laden's number one. We know that
Zahedi is number two. Muhammad Atef was
number three. We killed him in October
of 01. So that means Abu Zuba must be
the number three, right? Cuz he's out
doing all this different stuff, right?
>> And it turned out he wasn't actually.
You know, this this is what makes this a
sad story. And and this is why I would
be willing to talk to Abu Zabeta. And
this is why I am willing to talk to his
attorney because first of all, he was
not the terrorist Superman we thought he
was. He was a bad guy. So if he was a
bad guy, he should have been charged
with a crime and put on trial as the
Constitution says that he should and he
should face his accusers in a court of
law. Well, we know from the Senate
torture report that the CIA will never
permit him to be charged in a court of
law. And in fact, the torture report
tells us that the CIA has made a policy
decision that Abu Zubeda will never
leave Guantanamo
ever. And when he does die, eventually
he'll be cremated and his ashes thrown
into the Caribbean.
So remember, this is a guy who has never
been charged with a crime. So why
>> hold him, right?
>> What is their reasoning or what is their
explanation for that? They [__] it up
and they can't let any more get out into
the public. Kiryaku was bad enough
blabbing that, you know, we tortured
him. But then the Senate torture report
actually lays it all out blowby-blow by
blow what they did to him. And then if
we if we release him, what? He's going
to be on every TV channel in the world
talking about the torture that he
underwent at the hands of the Americans.
The CIA can't allow that.
>> What would what would you say to him? I
would say that I'm sorry for the way
he's been treated. Nobody deserves to be
treated this way. If he was the killer
that we said he was, he should have been
tried and convicted and punished
accordingly. If he was not the killer
that we said he was, he should be
released. Khalik Muhammad is the he is
the earthly incarnation of Satan. Khalik
Muhammad is a perplexing character
because, you know, he was an exchange
student here. He went to he went to some
state university in North Carolina,
lived with an American family. He's
utterly Americanized, but he
self-radicalized when he went back to uh
the Middle East or or to Pakistan.
>> Mhm.
>> He devoted many many years to hatching
plans or plots to kill as many Americans
as he possibly could. Well, before 9/11,
there's something you and I have
discussed in the past called the Bojinka
plot. So the Bojinka plot was an idea
that Khales Muhammad came up with in the
Philippines to hijack. It was something
like 710
747s and to fly them all into buildings
up and down the west coast of the United
States. He actually had a chance of that
plot working and he had all these papers
laid out, maps, drawings,
notes, and he left his apartment and
housekeeping went in to the apartment to
clean the apartment. And the housekeeper
is looking at this like, "What the heck
is all this stuff? I better call the
police." She calls the police. They
said, "This looks like the plans for a
terrorist attack." And so they set out
to look for him. They didn't know his
name. They only knew him by the name
Mkhtar, which I think you and I have
talked about in the past, but he
escaped. He escaped from Manila. So, we
knew that there was this very bad dude
out there known as Mkhtar who was
plotting this massive terrorist attack
uh that would take place on the West
Coast. So, we knew that Mkhtar was
involved in the planning for 9/11. As it
turned out, 9/11 was completely his
idea, but we didn't know who he was. We
didn't know what his real name was. And
that was one of the two most important
things that Abu Zuba gave us in his in
his FBI uh interviews.
>> Oh wow.
>> Yeah. He actually laughed at the FBI
agent Ali Sufan uh when Ali said, "We
didn't know who Mktar was." He's like,
"How can you not know who Mktar was?
He's the most dangerous man in the
world." And he said, "We don't know."
"Oh, it's Khaled Shake Muhammad.